Dear venerables, I have heard you say that\h
reflecting on death and impermanence should
lead to dissatisfaction and despair. And I can't\h
help but disagree. When I reflect on death and
impermanence, it inspires a sense of appreciation\h
for what I have and lets me enjoy these things
while I'm fortunate enough to have them. What role\h
would you say that this appreciation plays in the\hpractice?
If appreciation means you're\hoverlooking...
You just have to ask yourself,
while you're appreciating those things: How does\h
it feel to imagine that they would be
immediately taken away next second? Does\h
that feel like you're even more prepared for that
scenario and you're unmoved by it now, or does that\h
feel like something that you don't want to think about?
And if it feels like the latter, then that's\h
not the contemplation of death. So yes,
the contemplation of death would lead to joy\h
and burdenlessness to the degree that you have
given up attachments, to the degree that even the\h
things that are pleasant, you don't depend
on them anymore; you don't expect them to last.\h
That's the whole point: that there is not
even an emotional expectation that\hwould
have you surprised if those things were to
disappear next moment and then you would\h
be appreciating not the things, because that's
the whole point: they're inherently uncertain,
they could be taken away any moment.
You're not appreciating that. You're appreciating\h
the burdenlessness, you're appreciating the
absence of craving and that's the goal of the\h
actual contemplation of death. So even
more broadly as well, ask yourself:
How do I end up living my day
and my life when I reflect on death? If it's the actual\h
reflection on death, it should naturally lead\h\h
to renunciation, to giving up of desires, because\h
it becomes absolutely undeniable how pointless
all those things are. It doesn't give you more...\h
it doesn't increase their significance.
And just imagine: you go to a party and then you
know in advance that you're going to be forced to\h
go out at the worst possible moment. You already
know that from the start. Right at the\h
apex of your enjoyment, you're going to
be just kicked out. And then you would\h
think twice to actually go there, because you would
realize: even the enjoyment that\h
you could factually get is completely flattened\hout,
becomes completely worthless when\h
it stops seeming like you're in control of it.
You can't guarantee that you'll have as much\h
of it as you want. It actually becomes clear:
Oh, it would be better not to even begin enjoying\h
myself, because then I won't have anything
to be disappointed for. And that's the threat
of the contemplation of death.
you wouldn't commit to any direction of\h
any enjoyment, because you see the imminent
disappointment that lies at the end of it, and\h
then you realize: Oh actually that place of\h\h
ultimate non-committal is what's actually\h
pleasant. Not none of those other things could
even rival the relief that you would get\h
from that, because you always have that weight
at the back of your mind even if you don't think\h
about it, of knowing: Oh, this could be taken away,
and you might be taking steps to protect it,\h
steps that work, but that need to take steps
to protect it is already unpleasant.
One example I gave before: when you have car
and then know as good as that car might be,
and you might live\h\h
in a safe country or whatever, but you feel this\h
sense of: I need to protect it somehow. I need
to put an alarm on it. I need to make sure that\h
it's not going to get scratched. And all of those\h\h
activities that you need to exert in order to\h
protect the things that you enjoy, even if they're
experiences, even if they're people, not just\h
material possessions, that effort is inherently
stressful. And so the recognition of death should\h
lead you to see the fallacy of any setup of that
kind, even on the mental level.
If something is as spiritual or internal as it\h\h
might feel, if there is that sense that it could\h
just cease, could be taken away, then that's not\h\h
the right kind of peace. So, should we not protect\h
our things? Should we let them be liable
to destruction since that's their inevitable\h
doom? Well, you should certainly come to terms
with that scenario. Whatever steps towards\h
protection you take shouldn't be at the expense
of the recognition that it could be taken away at\h
any moment. And then if that backdrop is there the
entire time, the attempts of protection that are\h
completely useless and unwholesome: you won't be
able to do them because they can only happen when\h
you pretend it's not liable to be taken away.
So even in the suttas you would see that the Buddha
would make attempts to maintain his health.
But the difference is:
if that attempt were not to work and it would\h
produce even the opposite of the desired results,
he wouldn't be surprised, because from the very\h
start he had the context that: Oh, this is
out of my hands. So it's about that context,\h
about maintaining that context, because if
you were to let's say commit to never protecting\h
things, fundamentally you can only really...
you will have to fail in that determination\h
with something; you won't be able to extend it
to everything. And then with that one thing, you\h
would still pretend as if it's ultimately in your control,
and that means you hold the exact same\h
wrong view, even though the space of
it might have shrunk, you're still pretending\h
there is something that can be permanent.